Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
Perturbed by the thoughts on my mind
no matter how hard I try to sever my love.
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
I could give away my crown for the beauty by my side,
but the wheel of fortune turns weals into woes,
and woes into weals.
No one is the master of their own destiny,
the vicissitudes throughout their life.
For the lovers of all time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
There is no need to review it, Your Majesty.
For the past month, His Majesty
has stayed exclusively with Noble Lady An
except for a couple of times with Your Majesty.
What a humble family she comes from!
Why did she get the title of Noble Lady in just a year?
Noble Lady An ...
is "an old crow that jumped to a high branch".
Lady An's family is humble,
but at least her father is an official.
The prior emperor's Consort Liang was a slave
before she became a Consort.
You might not be aware, but
humble women have their own skills.
They know how to do the humble things
which we can't learn to do.
You two seem very happy. What are you talking about?
We were saying that although it's been hot during the day,
the wind is very cooling in the evenings.
It is nice to have the cooling wind
when the summer is about to end.
But when the wind blows over the ears into the heart,
it makes the heart cold.
His Majesty has been grieved by the loss of two children.
Since we are all in service to His Majesty,
did anyone come up with a good idea to lighten his spirits?
I arranged a banquet
and you made your toasts.
However, His Majesty was still dispirited.
And all of you were at your wits' end.
Now finally someone relieved the pain in His Majesty's heart.
You should be happy about it
instead of gossiping privately.
Noble Lady An does not have a glorious background.
But now His Majesty favors her,
and that means she's also in my favor.
I would normally turn a blind eye to jealousy in the harem.
But right now she is at the very center of His Majesty's heart.
If you cause her trouble,
you will trouble both myself and His Majesty.
Is that understood?
Yes, Your Majesty.
Sit down.
Yes.
Lady An is modest and mild-mannered.
She is the best person to soothe His Majesty's aching heart.
The tenderness in a woman is always
the medicine for a man's sorrow.
If you are truly upset by it,
just think of it as medicine for His Majesty.
Your Majesty has long served His Majesty
and knows who is the best to soothe His Majesty.
We concubines will not quibble.
I was out of ideas.
If any of you had been able to gain His Majesty's interest,
I wouldn't have troubled myself to arrange Lady An's performance!
Now that Noble Lady Chun is gone,
and Consort Nian has lost His Majesty's favor,
and Noble Lady Fuca and Concubine Sourire haven't fully recovered from their miscarriages,
The harem is fading.
But if we were to bring in hundreds of
candidates for a concubine selection,
you would only be more upset.
Your Majesty is right.
We will never be hard on Lingrong.
As long as His Majesty is happy with Lingrong's service.
Concubine Sourire, don't take it as a personal affront.
His Majesty needs company.
I'm glad that you are close with Noble Lady An.
I hope she can assuage His Majesty's grief.
Everything I have done is for His Majesty.
Your Majesty need not say that.
Your Majesty did it for His Majesty.
I don't feel there was an injustice.
I know you always see the big picture
and that His Majesty favors you.
But I see you mourning for your unborn child,
and your health not improving ...
There should always be someone serving His Majesty.
You must restore your health before you can serve His Majesty again.
I will obey Your Majesty's order.
I sympathize over the injustices you suffered because of Consort Nian.
The Empress Dowager also grieves for your loss.
I heard that Her Majesty has been feeling much better today.
You should pay your respects to her.
Yes.
Sourire.
How can I help you, Lady Fuca?
You look much better now.
That is because of Lady An, isn't it?
When she gains favor,
it should lift your spirits also.
That's how sisters help each other, isn't it?
I am on my way to pay respects to the Empress Dowager.
I take my leave now.
"A distinguished person is always busy."
You cannot see His Majesty
but you can see the Empress Dowager.
You really are a devoted concubine.
I cannot compare to you.
I’ve always stayed out of your way
“like the well water stays out of the river”.
Why, today,
are you making such snide comments?
We both serve His Majesty.
Why would I find fault with you?
I just thought that
since everyone knows Lady An is very close to you,
it was surely your idea. And you sought Her
Majesty's help in your effort to please His Majesty.
You always seem to have some
clever tricks up your sleeve.
I think I understand this one.
Since you've done all you can to advance Lady An,
if she has a child one day,
it will be your child as well.
In that case, losing your own child won't matter anymore.
I thought we could commiserate with each other for the same loss.
It turns out that you have already forgotten your pain.
You ...
Noble Lady Fuca.
Have you been imitating the walk
of the ladies from early Qin Dynasty?
I didn't expect Lady An to recognize this style of walking.
I always thought you were an uneducated person.
I heard that you practiced this way of walking
specifically to perform for His Majesty.
The ladies in Qin Dynasty walked like graceful willows swaying in the breeze.
Today I've seen how it looks.
I believe that
His Majesty will leave his sadness behind when he sees you walk.
I didn't expect your tastes to elevate so quickly
after serving His Majesty for just a few days.
Yes.
His Majesty was just saying the opera house
interpreted some of the classics terribly.
One was "Copy the Way They Walk in Handan"
and the other was "The Ugly Dongshi Imitating the Beautiful Xishi".
Now that I see
that your act is better than
those performers,
I think His Majesty will forget his
disappointment in them when he sees you.
How dare you make fun of me?
I dare not.
But just as Her Majesty said,
it doesn't matter what we learn,
as long as it lifts His Majesty's spirits.
Isn't that why you learned to walk like that?
Her Majesty will be pleased once she knows about this.
Do you really think the Empress likes you?
She's just using you as "dog skin plaster" on a wound.
Don’t be so full of yourself!
The plaster is useful if it works.
But unfortunately,
if you use a rotten plaster,
the wound will stink and people will avoid you.
Sorry that I came late.
You had to endure that because of me.
It was nothing.
I shouldn’t have responded to her.
I was always the one to help you out.
Now things have changed.
Are you blaming me, Sourire?
I'm not.
Do you blame me for not telling you about it?
It was all planned at the last minute.
Her Majesty urged me not to tell
anyone in order to surprise His Majesty,
and lighten his spirits.
I was not in a position to disobey Her Majesty.
I also thought that
if His Majesty favored me,
it would be helpful to you, too.
Things would be better for you.
Lingrong.
You should have let me know that your throat had recovered.
It worried me,
and took me by surprise.
You understand - there are orders we obey even if unwillingly.
Just like bulrushes which perish in autumn,
the favor I gain will last only as long as my voice.
I understand.
Everyone in the palace has to act contrary to their feelings sometimes.
I know.
Lady Fuca made me angry
but I made you sad.
If you keep crying,
I will be crying with you.
I bow in respect before Your Majesty.
Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
You two may leave.
Yes, Your Majesty.
Come sit next to me.
I thank Your Majesty.
I used to think highly of Shilan.
She has a decisive mind
and a beautiful face.
True, her temper tantrums were indulged.
But that is understandable for someone
who comes from a distinguished family.
I never knew that
she was such a vicious woman.
I’m aging
and my energy wanes.
I handed everything over to the Empress.
It is because of her incompetence that all of this has happened.
Palace affairs are like intertwined threads.
It is hard for Her Majesty to manage alone.
I hope Your Majesty will not blame Her Majesty.
You're still worried about the others, Sourire.
Your face looks pale, devoid of your usual rosy glow.
You must still be grieving your unfortunate child.
You are still young and new to the palace.
The face of a woman fades faster than the flowers.
Even the most beautiful face cannot
withstand the passing of time.
There will be no turning back to youth.
For some time, you've been wallowing in your grief.
Have you thought about how this makes the Emperor feel?
If you're not thinking about him,
you've lost only a child's life this time,
next time, you could lose your own.
I recognize my offence.
It's not about that.
Take care of yourself
and take care of the Emperor.
That will relieve me of my worries.
Yes.
You should return and have a good rest.
You need to listen to me.
Don’t be sad anymore.
I thank Your Majesty.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
Proceed.
Yes.
My Lady,
why are you writing?
The Empress Dowager and the Empress taught me
that writing calms the heart.
It's too loud outside.
How can anyone stay calm when she's trilling nonstop?
There are so many things in the world that can't be stopped.
Especially Lingrong’s singing.
It won't be blocked by a door.
My Lady, ever since you lost your child,
how many times has she visited?
She visited infrequently when she got the cough,
but even less now that she's in favor.
All she does is sing.
I'm not listening!
She was out of favor for such a long time.
Now that she has regained it, she must put His Majesty first.
Being physically present is not important...
It's the thought that matters.
Jade, grind the ink.
My Lady, His Majesty used to "trim the candle
wick at the west window" with you.
He "used to", as you said.
Singing and dancing are more entertaining
than poetry and literature.
Even the best book will be put aside once you grow tired of it.
Just like this fan.
You're unwilling to put it down in the summer,
but will not even touch it when autumn comes.
My Lady.
Why are you pitying this fan?
I have the same thoughts as Jade.
Aren't you suspicious about the speed and
the timing of Lingrong's recovery?
So what if I am suspicious?
She's in her prime.
Why should she wither away like me?
One lonely person is enough for my empty palace.
Stop.
Peace to Your Majesty.
I haven't seen you in a while. What has been keeping you busy?
I have been assisting Consort Estime with
the prayer ceremonies at Baohua Hall
so I have not had the time to pay respects to Your Majesty.
Although Consort Estime has been busy,
I have seen her a few times.
I've been concerned about Concubine Sourire's lost child.
So I have also been praying for her child,
hoping her child will arrive soon at the Pure Land.
That effort must have been hard on you.
It is only physical and mental labor for me.
But for Concubine Sourire, the emotional exhaustion is unbearable.
I misspoke. I beg Your Majesty's pardon.
To the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Your Majesty, the Empress Dowager is expecting you.
I'm worried about Concubine Sourire.
To the Palace of Pearl Jade.
His Majesty the Emperor.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Where is Concubine Sourire?
My Lady is sleeping in the chamber.
Is she feeling better?
I have an unintelligent tongue.
Your Majesty will know once you see her.
You dwell on the child even when you sleep.
Are you still aggrieved with me?
I still have matters to attend to.
Since she's asleep, you don't need to tell her that I visited.
Now that you have Lady An,
why do you still seem unhappy?
I went to check on Concubine Sourire just now.
She still hasn't gotten over the loss?
I ... can't bear seeing her so sad;
I don't want to see her like that.
When I see her unhappiness, it makes me angry.
I'm angry at myself
and angry at her for making me angry.
Then she is at fault.
As a concubine,
the emperor should matter more to her than herself.
You have been overly indulgent to her
and spoiled her.
I always thought she was more sensible than this.
If that's the case,
why don't you stop visiting her for now?
If she is wise, then she will come around.
I was thinking the same.
I'll visit her again once she has thought it through.
That's good.
Lady An will be devoted to your service.
You should head back to the Hall of Mental Cultivation now.
Certainly.
I'll visit tomorrow, Imperial Mother.
His Majesty departs.
Your Majesty, aren't you quite fond of Concubine Sourire?
Why did you advise His Majesty to not visit her?
I know my own son all too well.
He cares too much about Concubine Sourire.
That's why he gets upset when she's sad.
Ultimately, he is just upset about himself.
If they keep seeing each other,
I'm afraid it will create a permanent rift between them.
That would truly disappoint Concubine Sourire.
Your Majesty truly cares for Concubine Sourire.
An emperor is allowed to have a beloved concubine.
He cannot, however, be exclusively devoted to just one concubine.
That would bring chaos to the harem.
Now that Consort Nian is out of favor,
if Concubine Sourire becomes the dominant concubine,
the harem will lose its balance.
And her personality is not mild.
It's like a knife that needs to be blunted.
Your Majesty is wise and farsighted.
I don't see things more clearly than others.
I have just lived longer in the palace than them.
Your Majesty.
General Longkodo wishes to pay respects to Your Majesty.
He is concerned with Your Majesty's health.
Tell him
everything's fine.
He is an external family member. He shouldn't enter the harem.
It's not a necessary trip.
Yes.
Does Your Majesty not want to see him?
It wasn't easy to ease the tension between me and the Emperor.
If he knows that Longkodo visits me,
even if he says nothing about it,
he will still be upset.
We are not young anymore.
Why should we meet again?
The chrysanthemums were usually yellow and white.
But we have a lot of red, pink, and purple this year.
Bright colors bring the garden back to life
just like the spring.
The palace grows rare chrysanthemums cultured into vibrant colors.
Unlike the unworldly beauty of the chrysanthemums
that Tao Yuanming planted in his solitude.
Our worldly wisdom doesn't appreciate
the qualities chrysanthemums symbolize.
The flowers to decorate the palace
are probably required to be brightly colored.
Is that a word of caution?
I said that thoughtlessly.
What palace are we at?
This is the Hall of Prolonged Celebration,
where Consort Honnête resides.
Consort Honnête has visited me before
but I've never returned the visit.
I didn't expect it to be so out of the way.
Her Highness is ill.
She needs a quiet palace for her recovery.
The weather hasn't been kind lately.
I heard Her Highness's condition has gotten worse.
She made two pairs of shoes for my child when I was pregnant.
Now that she's ill,
I cannot pass her gate without entering.
Please go knock.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Peace to Your Highness.
Aren't you Her Highness's personal maid?
Why did you answer the door yourself?
Where's Her Highness?
I'm glad Your Highness is here.
Please come in.
Why is there no one else in the palace?
Her Highness fell ill a few years ago.
Her Majesty didn't assign any other
concubines to live with Her Highness
so that she could have a quiet residence.
What about the other servants?
Did they all move away?
Her Highness sent them away.
Her Highness doesn't look well.
What have the doctors said?
Her Highness said she would just keep taking her old medicine.
With so many occurrences in the palace,
she would not trouble the doctors.
Her Highness is unduly cautious.
She rightfully deserves to see a doctor.
This is not good.
Auspice.
Bring Dr. Wen here from the Imperial Infirmary.
Yes, Your Highness.
Jinxi.
It's necessary for Her Highness
to have more servants to take care of her.
Send a reliable maid from our palace to work here.
Certainly.
Lie down, Your Highness.
What brings you here?
I was passing by Your Highness's palace.
I heard that Your Highness is unwell so I came to visit.
It's nothing new.
I have seizures when the season changes.
It doesn't matter.
Your Highness's health matters.
Your Highness must take good care of it.
I haven't seen you for a while.
You've slimmed down so much.
How are you recovering?
Your Highness doesn't have many servants in your palace
but Your Highness has perceptive eyes and ears.
You perceive the palace affairs
without stepping out of your palace.
What I know is just superficial.
A child is the lifeblood of the mother.
Even an unborn child
is cherished like "heart and liver".
Your sudden loss
must be devastating.
It was a sudden loss.
But I had taken strong medicine before that.
It might have hurt my health.
We don't know that for certain.
I'm afraid what was more hurtful to you is
His Majesty's punishment for Nian Shilan.
She wanted to imitate how Empress Première
punished a Lord Consort.
I thought His Majesty
would execute her for you.
But from my perspective,
Nian Shilan is so stupid
to let this happen when she was managing the harem.
My supposition is that
she was trying to re-establish her authority.
If she knew you would have a miscarriage,
she would be the first one to feel afraid.
Her cleverness became her grief.
Whether it was accidental or intentional.
My only regret
is that I can't avenge my child.
I've endured all these years with my illness.
I'm in no hurry. Why are you?
“One might escape acts of Heaven, but
not punishment from the injustices one commits.”
We will wait.
I bow in respect before Your Highness.
Auspice, go see if the tonic is ready for Consort Honnête.
I have some questions for Dr. Wen.
Yes.
If you start taking care of Consort Honnête,
will she be able to fully recover?
Even if it was the legendary doctor Hua Tuo,
Consort Honnête would not be able to have children.
I will do my utmost to ensure Her Highness will regain her health.
No wonder she adores the children in the palace.
If that’s cast in stone,
I can only hope you will restore her health
so she will stop suffering in illness and pain.
I will do everything I can.
There's one thing I wish to ask you.
Your Highness need not withhold it.
I have thought my miscarriage was due to the Pleasancy
which caused it to happen after kneeling for just an hour.
That incense is heavy with musk
so it could have greatly damaged my health.
But prior to this,
I never stayed at her palace for over eight hours each day.
Does it really have such overpowering effects?
The more I think about it,
I had already started to feel slightly unwell
a few days before going to her palace.
How would you explain that?
My food was always tested for poison
so there wasn't something amiss in my diet.
What could have been causing my discomfort?
Your Highness has been thinking a lot about it.
Do you already have a suspicion?
The herbs you prescribed
to help me avoid serving His Majesty -
would they be harmful to me?
Could they have made me susceptible to miscarriages?
When I prescribed the herbs for you,
I controlled the dosage very carefully.
And you did not experience any discomfort after.
So it's not likely that the herbs could cause miscarriage.
However ...
It depends on one's constitution.
Your Highness was poisoned by Yu.
It's possible that the poison had lasting effects.
Maybe ...
It was partially my fault.
Wasn't it?
My Lady, it is past.
Whether it was because of Nian or Pleasancy,
you should only remember that it was their fault.
You must stop putting any blame on yourself.
My Lady, why did you leave by yourself?
I've been looking for you.
It's my fault for not getting back sooner.
Sorry about the wait.
Were you crying?
It's just the dust.
It is a bit windy today.
Let's go back so you can have a rest.
Your Majesty hasn't visited Sourire for some time.
Will Your Majesty visit her tonight?
It's not that I don't want to visit her.
I'm also sad about the loss of a child.
But she has such a strong personality.
I wish she was half as mild-mannered as you are.
Please forgive her if she ever upset Your Majesty
considering her painful loss.
This isn't easy on her.
Nor is it on me.
Why doesn't she think from my perspective?
You two are like sisters to each other.
You understand her better than anyone else.
Sourire comes from a distinguished family and is very well-learned.
I have always admired her.
I hope Your Majesty will favor her just as before.
Sourire hasn't been thinking sensibly, and that is why
she's unable to serve Your Majesty.
It might be for the best if Your Majesty does not visit her for now
to avoid any undesired confrontations.
I will keep encouraging Sourire to think reasonably
so both of you can be happy.
That is just my humble opinion.
I hope Your Majesty does not mind it.
You are very considerate towards Concubine Sourire and me.
There's nothing to disapprove of.
I'm flattered.
I simply like Your Majesty to always be happy.
I have no skills like Sourire's
to offer advice to Your Majesty.
You should not look down upon yourself.
You and Sourire are like
"the spring flower and the autumn moon".
You both have your own merits.
So ...
Does Your Majesty like Sourire
more than me?
At this moment,
I like you more.
Your Majesty has been working hard.
I picked some loquat leaves.
I will have them simmered with rock sugar
to help relieve Your Majesty's cough.
It will also taste better.
Thank you for doing it personally.
My Lady, it's time for your medicine.
My Lady still didn't take it?
I wonder what she saw that day.
She has been like this ever since.
She is so severely ill.
But His Majesty hasn't visited for over a half-month.
She refuses to take medicine.
I've reported to Mr. Su quite a few times.
And the Empress has been informed too.
But His Majesty hasn't come.
Looks like His Majesty won't.
The Palace of Earthly Honor and the Palace of Pearl Jade
used to be the most lively palaces.
Now they are both cold and quiet.
"One fails, all fail."
But My Lady is ...
Why are you two sitting outside?
It's cold out here.
What brings you here?
Lady An heard that My Lady is ill.
So she asked me to send some ejiao cakes
from the Imperial Kitchen.
Please thank Lady An for me.
Lady An has a lot of tasks and errands.
I should return now.
She never visited the entire time.
But she still calls My Lady her sister.
Leave it.
What does Daisy know? Don't be angry at her.
This upsets me too.
I'll give it to Xiao-Yunzi.
Sure.
My Lady is ill.
No one will visit her except Dr. Wen.
It took some effort to get the herbs.
I will reheat the medicine for My Lady.
I will request an audience with His Majesty tomorrow.
If I bring His Majesty here,
we don't need anyone's pity gifts.
Your Majesty.
Yes?
The Palace of Pearl Jade sent someone here.
Concubine Sourire is ill.
They hope Your Majesty will visit her when you're available.
I see.
Tell them I will go when I am available.
Yes.
Your Majesty was already aware of Her Highness's illness.
But certainly, I know Your Majesty has been busy.
I have, Su Peisheng.
But I
also don't want to see her.
If Your Majesty will enlighten me.
I've asked Dr. Wen.
Concubine Sourire's illness is caused by her sadness.
It's because of the loss of her child after all.
I'd rather not see her, because
then we make each other sad.
She will be fine when she overcomes her sorrow.
I will tell her servant Jade that
Your Majesty will go when you're available.
Peace to Lady An.
Rise.
You seem to be coming from the Hall of Mental Cultivation.
Were you summoned by His Majesty?
My Lady has been ill.
His Majesty asked me to report to him.
So did His Majesty visit Sourire?
Not yet.
His Majesty has been as busy as you, My Lady.
Does Sourire blame me for not visiting her?
I need to serve His Majesty.
I'm afraid Sourire might feel upset when she sees me.
So I didn't want to visit her.
Jade, has Sourire been feeling better?
Thanks for asking, My Lady.
She will be better soon.
I'm glad to hear that.
Lady An, I venture to ask you
to remind His Majesty when you see him
that your "sister" is ill in the Palace of Pearl Jade.
I believe if you do so,
My Lady will get better sooner.
Certainly.
I always talk about Sourire when I'm with His Majesty.
It's just that His Majesty has been
very busy with state affairs.
But don't worry.
I will certainly talk to His Majesty about this.
I thank you in advance, Lady An.
Go.
Jade was disrespectful to you, My Lady.
Will you still speak for Concubine Sourire
when you meet His Majesty?
Jade is Sourire's dowry maid.
Her disrespect is the same as Sourire's.
However,
I will talk about it when appropriate.
Su Peisheng.
Your Majesty.
I'll go visit ...
Your Majesty, Lady An has arrived.
All right, I will meet her in the west chamber.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Subscription: https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Lonely Phoenix
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
I dimly recall the colorful blooms in every summer.
They are as distant as the autumn moon in the water.
He loved me with a volatile heart.
And before I knew it, we fell apart.
Behind me are the promises and longing.
Before me lie the flute and the zither.
I loved you with my body and soul
But you hurt me from head to toe.
My wish ran athwart
and I ended up a fool of my destiny.
My love was the wind-swept flowers from a tree.
A plum bloomed in winter hoping for a fruitful summer.
But the irresistible winds of destiny destroyed her wish.
You can hear the flapping of a phoenix
but you will never see it.
What you see is the falling leaves from the phoenix tree.
The falling leaves from the phoenix tree.